Md. Nazmul **Haque**

Utility Building - 306, Islamic University of Technology, Gazipur, Dhaka - 1704.

□ (+88) 01786870220 | ■ nazmul.haque@iut-dhaka.edu | 🖸 Shisir | 🖹 orbit | 🛅 nazmul-haque-6b8bb8132

Summary

Currently, I am a Lecturer at Islamic University of Technology (IUT), Bangladesh. Former Software Engineer at Samsung R&D Institute, Bangladesh. Masters and Bachelors in Software Engineering from Institute of Information Technology (IIT), University of Dhaka. I am interested in machine learning, especially deep learning based research area. Check this out on my portfolio.

Work Experience

Islamic University of Technology (IUT)

Dhaka, Bangladesh

LECTURER

July 2021 - Present

Taking different courses such as Design patterns, Embedded software development, Web programming, Engineering drawing lab and so on

Samsung R&D Institute Bangladesh

Dhaka, Bangladesh

SOFTWARE ENGINEER

April 2018 - Jan. 2019

• Windows Application Development Team in Mobile Application Group 2 (MAG2)

Institute of Information Technology, University of Dhaka

Dhaka, Bangladesh

COURSE INSTRUCTOR

Jan. 2019 - August 2020

• Worked as an instructor in different short courses regarding "Matlab, Origin and Latex", "Web design using HTML/CSS/JavaScript" and "Office Application for Smart Office"

Datasoft System Bangladesh Limited

Dhaka, Bangladesh

SOFTWARE ENGINEER INTERN

Jan. 2017 - June 2017

- Involved with developing two in-house automation projects
- One project was developed using programming language C# and MVC .NET web framework

Education

Institute of Information Technology(IIT), University of Dhaka

Dhaka, Bangladesh

MASTER OF SCIENCE IN SOFTWARE ENGINEERING

Jan. 2019 - June 2020

- CGPA: 3.85/4.00 (Position 3^{rd})
- Masters Thesis: Feature selection on high dimension low sample size data

Institute of Information Technology(IIT), University of Dhaka

Dhaka, Bangladesh

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN SOFTWARE ENGINEERING

Jan. 2014 - Dec. 2017

• CGPA: 3.81/4.00

Abdul Karim Sarkar College, Tanore, Rajshahi

Rajshahi, Bangladesh

HIGHER SECONDARY SCHOOL CERTIFICATE

2012 - 2013

• GPA: 5.00/5.00

Ramgaon Shahapur (R.S) High School, Naogaon

Rajshahi, Bangladesh

SECONDARY SCHOOL CERTIFICATE

2006 - 2011

• GPA: 5.00/5.00

Publications

Journals

- 1. **Md. Nazmul Haque**, Sadia Sharmin, Amin Ahsan Ali, Abu Ashfaqur Sajib, Mohammad Shoyaib. "Use of relevancy and complementary information for discriminatory gene selection from high-dimensional gene expression data". PLOS ONE 16(10): e0230164, October 2021. **[Q1 journal, IF: 3.752]** [PDF]
- 2. Maksuda Islam, M. Safayat Hossen, Ahsanul Haque, Md. Nazmul Haque, Lutfun Nahar Lota. "The Integrity of Source Code Commenting: Benchmark Dataset and Empirical Analysis". Software Quality Journal (2022), [Q1 journal, IF: 2.132] [Submitted]
- 3. Abdus Salam, Md Riad Sarkar Pavel, Shahid Uz Zaman, Khaled Shaifullah Joy, **Md. Nazmul Haque**, Farah Jeba, and Juwel Rana. "Economic and Health Burden Associated with the Ambient Air Pollution in 2 Bangladesh Over the Last Decade (2008-2019)". Science of the Total Environment Journal (2022), *[Q1 journal, IF: 10.753]* [Submitted]

1

4. Maliha Noushin Raida, Zannatun Naim Sristy, Nawshin Ulfat, Sheikh Moonwara Anjum Monisha, Md. Jubair Ibna Mostafa, **Md. Nazmul Haque**. "A Study on Classifying Stack Overflow Questions based on Difficulty by Utilizing Contextual Features". Journal of Systems and Software (2023), *[Q1 journal, IF: 3.514]* [Submitted]

Conferences

- 1. A. Al Jobair, Suzad Mohammad, Z. Raidah Maisha, Md. Jubair Ibna Mostafa, **Md. Nazmul Haque**. "An Empirical Study on Neophytes of Stack Overflow: How Welcoming the Community is towards Them." In Proceedings of the 17th International Conference on Evaluation of Novel Approaches to Software Engineering, ISBN 978-989-758-568-5, ISSN 2184-4895, pages 197-208. [PDF] [Core Rank: B]
- 2. Fazle Rabbi, **Md. Nazmul Haque**, Md. Eusha Kadir, Md. Saeed Siddik and Ahmedul Kabir, "An Ensemble Approach to Detect Code Comment Inconsistencies using Topic Modeling", *The 32nd International Conference on Software Engineering and Knowledge Engineering, SEKE 2020, KSIR Virtual Conference Center, USA, July 9-19, 2020. [PDF] [Core Rank: B]*
- 3. **Md. Nazmul Haque**, Mahir Mahbub, Md Hasan Tarek, Lutfun Nahar Lota, Amin Ahsan Ali, "Nurse care activity recognition: a GRU-based approach with attention mechanism" *In Adjunct Proceedings of the 2019 ACM International Joint Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing and the 2019 International Symposium on Wearable Computers (UbiComp/ISWC '19 Adjunct).* [PDF] [Core Rank: A*]
- 4. **Md. Nazmul Haque**, M Tanjid Hasan Tonmoy, Saif Mahmud, Amin Ahsan Ali, Muhammad Asif Hossain Khan, Mohammad Shoyaib, "GRU-based Attention Mechanism for Human Activity Recognition", *ICASERT-2019: 1st International Conference on Advances in Science, Engineering and Robotics Technology.* [PDF]
- 5. Sayeda Shamma Alia, **Md. Nazmul Haque**, Sadia Sharmin, Shah Mostafa Khaled, Mohammad Shoyaib, "Bug Severity Classification Based on Class-Membership Information", 2018 Joint 7th International Conference on Informatics, Electronics and Vision (ICIEV) and 2018 2nd International Conference on Imaging, Vision and Pattern Recognition (ICIVPR). [PDF]

Achievements

2020	ICT fellow, Awarded as an ICT fellow under ICT Division Bangladesh	Dhaka, Bangladesh
2018-19	ICT fellow, Awarded as an ICT fellow under ICT Division Bangladesh	Dhaka, Bangladesh
2007	Scholarship , Board scholarship in Junior Secondary	Rajshahi, Bangladesh
2004	Scholarship , Board scholarship in Primary	Rajshahi, Bangladesh

Academic Projects

Object detection

RESEARCH BASED ACADEMIC PROJECT

Jul. 2017 - Nov. 2017

- A deep learning approach that simultaneously detects different objects in a single image and objectness scores at each position.
- Python 2.7 and tensorflow framework for Development
- [github link]

Graduate Record Validation System

Course work Aug. 2017 - Oct. 2017

- A web-based system for validating a graduate student
- Developed using PHP, Laravel, MySQL
- [github link]

Event Management System

Worked in a Team with 4 members Sep. 2016 - Nov. 2016

- A web based event management application that provides most of the basic functionalities required for an event with event name, description, start date and duration. Each event may contain multiple sub-events, which will be managed by event creator called event manager.
- Event manager can turn off / on notification of own events, even for sub-events. It is allowed to change ownership of an event or even delete it
- To avoid repetitive creation of similar events, admin can add some template events. These are reusable for creating further similar events. Templates will have all similar fields and sub-events like an event except start date and description. Use of templates have advantages like auto-filled fields and auto added sub-events
- Members have choice to receive notification of events. Users will be notified for running and upcoming events. Every membership approval request will be sent to the event manager. System admins have full control over the system.
- Developed using PHP, MySQL.
- [github link]

Ekushey Online Code Editor

DEVELOPED AS A SINGLE PERSON PROJECT

Feb. 2016 - May 2016

- A web based code editor that provides programmers to write code with proper suggestions and templates on C and C++ programming languages.
- Developed using PHP, MySQL.
- [github link]

Call Graph

Worked in a Team with 3 members Feb. 2015 - May 2015

- A desktop based application to represent calling relationship between functions and variables in a C programming language.
- Provides better understanding of a program or as a basis for further analyses such as tracking the flow of values between procedures and the change of value of variables in a program.
- · Developed using Java.
- [github link]

Sudoku game

WORKED IN A TEAM WITH 2 MEMBERS

July. 2014 - Nov. 2014

- A desktop based application to play game with three different level (easy, medium, hard).
- · Provide hints to the players.
- · Developed using Java
- [github link]

Skills

Programming Python 3.5, Matlab 9.5 (R2018b), Java7/8, C, PHP7, Javascript, C#, C, C++

Frameworks ASP.NET MVC5, Angular 4.0, Angular JS, Bootstrap 3

Tools Anaconda, Pycharm, Eclipse Luna, Visual Studio 2015, Git

Operating System Linux (Ubuntu 14.04, 16.04, 18.04), Windows 8.1/10

Databases MySQL, Microsoft SQL Server

Extracurricular Activity _____

Artificial Intelligence Review Journal

International Journa

REVIEWER June 2020 - Present

Datasoft System Bangladesh Limited

Commencement ceremony

VOLUNTEER Mach 2017

Graduation Tour India

CORE ORGANIZER Feb. 2017 - Mar. 2017

Fresher Reception & Farewell program

IIT

CORE ORGANIZER 2016

DevOps Workshop

CORE ORGANIZER 2019

SUST IUPC & QAAIPC

 CONTESTANT
 2014-2015

Online Problem solving

PROBLEM SOLVER 2015-2018

- UVA online judge:146
- URI online judge: 165
- Code forces online judge-232
- lightOJ -56

References_

Dr. Mohammad Shoyaib

Professor

Institute of Information Technology University of Dhaka.

Email: shoyaib@du.ac.bd

Phone: +880 1938 406101

Dr. Abu Raihan Mostofa Kamal

Professor and Head

Department of Computer Science and Engineering (CSE)

Islamic University of Technology (IUT)

(A Subsidiary Organ of OIC)

Email: raihan.kamal@iut-dhaka.edu